Serge Diaghilev/Serge Lifar Collection
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
Serge Diaghilev/Serge Lifar Collection1750-1950 (bulk 1890-1929)
ML31.D53
Diaghilev, Serge, 1872-1929
around 1,350 items 81 boxes 91 linear feet
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
This collection is comprised in large part of printed music, widely representing 18th century Italian and 19th century Russian operatic music. Includes rare pre-revolutionary editions of Russian folk songs, annotated performance scores of Stravinsky, Mussorgsky, Rimsky-Korsakov, Gounod, Cimarosa. Non-musical materials include three letters from S. Prokofiev to S. Diaghilev, rare edition of books on music, literature and theater, libretti and synopses, souvenir books and programs and photographs. Several of the programs and photographs show Léon Bakst's set and costume designs. Non-musical materials also include Diaghilev’s personal notebook, containing entries in French, Russian, and English made in 1926-1929.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Bakst, Léon, 1866-1924.; Diaghilev, Serge, 1872-1929--Autographs.; Diaghilev, Serge, 1872-1929--Correspondence.; Diaghilev, Serge, 1872-1929.; Diaghilev, Serge, 1872-1929.; Lifar, Serge, 1905-1986.; Lifar, Serge, 1905-1986. Serge Diaghilev/Serge Lifar collection. 1750-1950.; Prokofiev, Sergey, 1891-1953--Correspondence.; Prokofiev, Sergey, 1891-1953.; Prokofiev, Sergey, 1891-1953.
Organizations
Ballets russes.
Subjects
Ballet--Costume.; Ballet--Stage-setting and scenery.; Composers--Correspondence.; Impresarios--Correspondence.; Operas--Librettos.; Operas--Scores.
Form/Genre
Correspondence.; Photographic prints.
Administrative Information
Provenance
Acquired; 1984.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Related Material
Three (3) original costume designs by Léon Bakst for the Ballets Russes’ production of The Sleeping Princess (1921) are currently housed in the Library of Congress Prints and Photographs Division.
Access and Restrictions
The Serge Diaghilev/Serge Lifar Collection is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Music Division prior to visiting in order to determine whether the desired materials will be available at that time.
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1872, Mar. 31 Sergei Pavlovich Diaghilev is born in Novgorod province, Russia, the only child of Pavel Pavlovich Diaghilev and Evgeniia Nikolaevna Essipova; Diaghilev's mother died as a result of the birth. Both of his parents were from old gentry landowner families. Pavel Pavlovich, a soldier in the Chevaliers Gardes in the service of the tsar, is transferred to St. Petersburg shortly afterwards
1874 Pavel Pavlovich Diaghilev marries Elena Valerianovna Panaeva, of whom Serge Diaghilev was very fond. Elena was from a musical family and was distantly related to Pëtr Il'ich Tchaikovsky. Through these family connections, Diaghilev is afforded the opportunity as a youth to meet many musicians and composers, among them Tchaikovsky (whom the young Diaghilev referred to as "Uncle Petia") and Modest Musorgsky
1882 Pavel Pavlovich is transferred to the provincial Russian town of Perm. They move into the family estate at nearby Bikbarda, which soon becomes an unofficial town cultural center
1890 Serge Diaghilev enters the university at St. Petersburg to study law, for which he has little enthusiasm. His interest and effort seem to be channeled into music, for he soon begins lessons in singing and composition. After a short period of study with Nikolai Rimsky-Korsakov, who advises him to reconsider a career in composition, Diaghilev begins to turn his attention more and more to art history and criticism
1891 Serge Diaghilev's first European trip takes him to Berlin, Paris, Rome, Venice, Florence and Vienna. The cultural life which he encounters in these cities has a profound effect on his developing artistic sensibility
1895-1896 During subsequent trips Diaghilev begins to purchase paintings which form the basis of a noteworthy collection. His first articles about contemporary art and painters are published. After six years at the university (in a customarily four-year program), Diaghilev completes his law degree
1899 Establishment of a series of ambitious art exhibitions, which meet with tremendous acclaim. Establishment of the review Mir Iskusstva (The World of Art), which includes writings on art, music and literature, as well as highly original graphics material. Appointed assistant to the Director of the Imperial Theaters; he resigns after a dispute with management in 1901
1903 The World of Art ceases publication due to disagreements and dissatisfaction on the part of contributors to the magazine
1905 "The Exhibition of Historical Russian Portraits," comprising over three thousand works, was organized by Diaghilev; the project takes three years and innumerable trips throughout Russia to complete. The Exhibition is held at the Tauride (Tavri-chevskiĭ) Palace in St. Petersburg and meets with an immense success. Similar exhibitions were organized the following year in Paris, Berlin and Venice. Serge Lifar is born in Kiev
1907 First series of Russian music concerts organized in Paris
1908 Concerts are expanded to include opera and ballet; opera productions include the first performances outside Russia of Rimsky-Korsakov's Sadko and Musorgsky's Boris Godunov, the latter achieving almost instantaneous worldwide popularity, and having a significant musical influence on French composers, including Debussy and Ravel
1909, May 19 First appearance of the Ballet Russe in Paris. Its immense success led to a resurgence of the ballet as an art form, especially in France and in Russia, as well as to the development of the field of ballet criticism
1910, June 25 Première of Stravinsky's ballet The Firebird, commissioned by Diaghilev for the Ballet Russe; this was the first of twelve works resulting from the collaboration between Diaghilev and Stravinsky
1911 The Ballet Russe is established at Monte Carlo
1912 Non-Russian artists become more frequently involved in the Ballet Russe productions: commissions are given to artists such as Debussy, Ravel, Hahn and Cocteau
1913, May 29 Première of the groundbreaking Le Sacre de printemps of Stravinsky (choreo-graphed by Nijinsky) which causes an unprecedented and legendary scandal
1917 Collaboration with Pablo Picasso, who designs sets and costumes for Satie's Parade
1923 Meeting with Serge Lifar at Monte Carlo, who, upon the recommendation of his teacher Bronislava Nijinska, was contracted to enter the Ballet Russe. By commissioning Stravinsky's Pulcinella, based on works of the eighteenth century masters Cimarosa, Scarlatti and Pergolesi, Serge Diaghilev influences the rise of neoclassicism in twentieth-century music
1925 Lifar has a principal role in the Ballet Russe production of Dukelsky's Zéphyr et Flore
1929, Aug. 19 Serge Diaghilev dies in Venice from complications resulting from diabetes. Lifar assumes the management of the Paris Opéra Ballet, a position which he holds (excluding the years 1944 through 1946, when he directs the Nouveau Ballet de Monte-Carlo) until 1959. During his tenure there he creates many new ballets, writes several books (including a biography of Diaghilev) and establishes new dance institutions. For his contributions to the art of ballet he is awarded the French Légion d'Honneur
1986 Serge Lifar dies
Scope and Content Note
He was neither a painter, nor a dancer, nor had extensive musical training, yet by means of his great organizational and managerial skills, as well as by a keen aesthetic sense and an unerring sense of style, Serge Diaghilev had a profound influence on the course of music, ballet and art in the twentieth century.
Diaghilev's musical interests spanned a wide range of styles, as reflected by the variety of musical material contained in this collection. A large part of this material represents musical works considered by Diaghilev for choreographic purposes and eventual production by the Ballet Russe; much of this material consequently bears annotations and performance indications.
This collection is comprised in large part of printed music, most of which emanated from the personal music library of Serge Diaghilev. This library was acquired by Lifar, a premier dancer with the Ballet Russe and a protégé of Diaghilev, who was present at the latter's deathbed. In his auto-biography, Ma Vie, Lifar recalls how Diaghilev had died without leaving a will, and that he was prompted to break into Diaghilev's Venice apartment and to smuggle out material from his library in order to prevent its dispersal.
The collection is particularly rich in the material of eighteenth-century Italian composers such as Paisiello, Pergolesi, and Cimarosa; nineteenth-century Russians such as Musorgsky, Rimsky-Korsakov, Tchaikovsky, Glinka, Dargomyzhsky and Liadov, as well as by several important collections of Russian folk song, all appearing in rare pre-Revolutionary editions; and nineteenth century French composers such as Chabrier, Gounod, Delibes and Godard. Also included are a significant number of popular works from the early Soviet period; several works for jazz band as well as popular songs from the early years of this century; heavily annotated chorus part books apparently used in the productions of Stravinsky's Les Noces, Rimsky-Korsakov's Snegurochka, and Musorgsky's Khovanshchina; and annotated performing scores of operas of Gounod (particularly La colombe, Philémon et Baucis, and Le médecin malgré lui) and Cimarosa for which Diaghilev commissioned new editions and/or additional musical material by composers such as Respighi, Satie, Milhaud and Auric. Particularly notable holograph material is represented in the collection by scores such as Respighi's recitatives for Cimarosa's Le astuzie femminili; Prokofiev's annotations to the printed score of his ballet Le pas d'acier; and one leaf of Stravinsky's arrangement for pianola of the "Berceuse" section from The Firebird. Among the non-musical material in the collection, particularly notable are three letters of Sergei Prokofiev to Diaghilev; rare editions of books on music, literature and theater; and Diaghilev's personal notebook, used from 1926 until his death in 1929, containing entries in French, Russian and English regarding planned productions, future projects, addresses, etc., made by Diaghilev, Lifar and Boris Kochno.
Russian transliterations follow the standard Library of Congress system wherever possible. Modifications, however, were incorporated due to the inaccessibility of certain computer-generated symbols, hence the use of the symbol "ĭ" for the Russian short "i" (i kratkoe) and the omission of ligatures over groupings of letters, such as those used to indicate Russian soft vowels.
In addition to printed music, the collection contains music manuscripts, correspondence, libretti and synopses, books and monographs, magazines, and Diaghilev's personal notebook, which the impresario used from 1926 until his death in 1929.
Three items purchased during the same auction are housed in the Prints and Photographs Division of the Library of Congress.
The approximate dates of the items in this collection range from about 1750, represented by several manuscripts, to about 1950, the date of several ballet scores added to the collection by Lifar. The majority of the material in the collection, however, dates from 1890 to 1929.
Kevin LaVine, June 1994
Organization of the Serge Diaghilev/Serge Lifar Collection
The Serge Diaghilev/Serge Lifar Collection is organized into four series:
I. Printed Music Material
II. Manuscript Music Material
III. Personal Papers
IV. Printed Material
http://lccn.loc.gov/2006568220
Container List
- I. Printed Music Material, 1750-1950 (Box 1-67)
  The series Printed Music Material is arranged into three subseries: General, Collections, and Miscellaneous. This series is represented by printed music and other materials from the personal music library of Serge Diaghilev.
  Arrangement is by format, composer and title.
  - A. General (Box 1-65)
    - Albéniz, Isaac
      - Chants d'Espagne, op. 232, no. 2: Orientale. Barcelona: Dotésio, n.d., Solo piano; score; 7 p.; Plate no. 22-2. (Box-folder 1/2)
      - Iberia, v. 1. Paris: Édition mutuelle, 1911., Solo piano; score; 33 p.; Plate no. E.3083.M. (Box-folder 1/3)
      - Iberia, v. 2. Paris: Édition mutuelle, 1907., Solo piano: score; 39 p.; Plate no. E.3084.M. (Box-folder 1/4)
      - Iberia, v. 3. Paris: Édition mutuelle, 1907., Solo piano; score; 46 p.; Plate no. E.3085.M. (Box-folder 1/5)
      - Iberia, v. 4. Paris: Édition mutuelle, 1907., Solo piano; score; 43 p.; Plate no. E.3086.M. (Box-folder 1/6)
      - Zortzico. Paris: Édition mutuelle, n.d., Solo piano; score; 7 p.; Plate no. E.3142.M. (Box-folder 1/7)
    - Aliab'ev, Aleksandr Aleksandrovich
      - Soloveĭ. Moscow: P. IUrgenson, 1901., Voice and piano; score; 3 p.; Plate no. 26559.; Language note: Russian; Language note: German (Box-folder 1/8)
    - Arkhangel'skiĭ, Aleksandr Andreevich
      - Chasy, op. 13a. Moscow: Izdanie Studiia, 1910., Voice and piano; score; 6 p.; Plate no. 596.; Language note: Russian (Box-folder 1/9)
      - Chërtovy kacheli, op. 23, no. 3. Moscow: A. Gutkheĭl', 1910., Voice and piano; score; 7 p.; Plate no. 9379.; Language note: Russian (Box-folder 1/10)
      - Kuranty, op. 23, no. 2. Moscow: Izdanie Studiia, 1910., Voice and piano; score; 8 p.; Plate no. 835.; Language note: Russian (Box-folder 1/11)
      - Maskarad, op. 34, no. 2: Petit morceau oublié. Moscow: B. Reshke, n.d., Cello and piano; cello part, piano score; 1 p.; 2 p.; Plate no. B.225.R. (Box-folder 1/12)
      - Maskarad, op. 34, no. 3: Danse des vingtièmes années. Moscow: B. Reshke, n.d., Solo piano; score; 5 p.; Plate no. B.226.R. (Box-folder 1/13)
      - Maskarad, op. 34, no. 4: Kogda pechal' slezoĭ nevol'noĭ (Romans Niny). Moscow: B. Reshke, n.d., Voice and piano; score; 5 p.; Plate no. B.227.R.; Language note: Russian (Box-folder 1/14)
      - Maskarad, op. 34, no. 5: Valse triste. Moscow: B. Reshke, n.d., Solo piano; score; 5 p.; Plate no. B.228.R. (Box-folder 1/15)
      - Piesnia o Komarie, op. 26, no. 1. Moscow: B. Reshke, n.d., Solo voice, chorus and piano; piano-vocal score; 7 p.; Plate no. B.218.R.; Language note: Russian (Box-folder 1/16)
      - Prélude, op. 10, no. 1. Moscow: Izdanie Studiia, 1913., Solo piano; score; 3 p.; Plate no. 1333.; p. 2 missing (Box-folder 1/17)
      - Raspakhnulos' okno, op. 21a. Moscow: [s.n.], 1910., Voice and piano; score; 5 p.; Plate no. K.570.M.; Language note: Russian (Box-folder 1/18)
      - Shelkovinka, op. 5c. Moscow: Kruzhka, 1908., Voice and piano; score; 6 p.; Also published Moscow: Izdanie Studiia, 1908; Plate no. K.670.S.; Language note: Russian (Box-folder 1/19)
      - Skazka o kurochkie i zolotom iaichkie, op. 26, no. 2. Moscow: B. Reshke, n.d., Voice and piano; score; 7 p.; Plate no. B.219.R.; Language note: Russian (Box-folder 1/20)
      - Starinnyĭ val's, op. 23, no. 1. Moscow: [s.n.], 1910., Voice and piano; score; 8 p.; Plate no. 951.; Language note: Russian (Box-folder 1/21)
      - U mashinki, op. 25, no. 1. Moscow: B. Reshke, 1913., Voice and piano; score; 7 p.; Plate no. B.235.R.; Language note: Russian (Box-folder 1/22)
      - Udovushka, udovushka moia, op. 26, no. 3. Moscow: B. Reshke, n.d., Voice and piano; score; 7 p.; Plate no. B.216.R.; Language note: Russian (Box-folder 1/23)
      - Viktoriia regiia, op. 36, no. 1. Moscow: Lira, 1914., Voice and piano; score; 3 p.; Plate no. K.625.M.; Language note: Russian (Box-folder 1/24)
      - Za nashim, za dvorom, op. 1, no. 3. Moscow: B. Reshke, 1913., Solo voices (TB), clarinet and tambourine; score; 3 p.; Plate no. B.230.R.; Language note: Russian (Box-folder 1/25)
    - Arne, Thomas
      - Comus See: I.B. Collections, Box 1 (Item S/62), p. 67
    - Auber, Daniel François Esprit
      - L'ambassadrice. Paris: G. Brandus, n.d., Piano-vocal score; 154 p.; Plate no. T.1497.; Plate number incomplete.; Language note: French (Box-folder S/1)
      - Barcarolle. Paris: RRandus [G. Brandus (?)], n.d., Piano-vocal score; 187 p.; Plate no. E.T.et Cie.1870.; Language note: French (Box-folder 2/1)
      - Il cavallo di bronzo. Milan: E. Sonzogno, 1875., Piano-vocal score; 342 p.; Plate no. E.S.70.; Language note: Italian (Box-folder 2/2)
      - La circassienne. Paris: Colombier, n.d., Piano-vocal score; 357 p.; Plate no. C.2587.; Contains sparse annotations in pencil and page markers. (Box-folder S/2)
      - Le domino noir. Paris: G. Brandus, n.d., Piano-vocal score; 172 p.; Plate no. T.1496.; Contains sparse annotations in pencil and page markers.; Language note: French (Box-folder S/3)
      - Fra Diavolo. Paris: P. Maquet, n.d., Piano-vocal score; 374 p.; Plate no. 8255.; Language note: French (Box-folder 2/3)
      - Le lac des fées. Paris: G. Brandus, n.d., Piano-vocal score; 416 p.; Also published Paris: S. Dufour, n.d.; Plate no. 9358.; Contains annotations in pencil, appearing mostly on contents page.; Language note: French (Box-folder S/4)
      - Lestocq. Paris: G. Brandus, n.d., Piano-vocal score; 260 p.; Plate no. T.1431.; Language note: French (Box-folder S/5)
      - Marco Spada. Paris: J. Meissonnier, n.d., Piano-vocal score; 304 p.; Plate no. J.M.3229.; Contains sparse annotations in pencil.; Language note: French (Box-folder S/6)
      - Le premier jour de bonheur. Paris: L. Escudier, n.d., Piano-vocal score; 226 p.; Plate no. L.E.2884.; Language note: French (Box-folder S/7)
      - La sirène. Paris: G. Brandus, n.d., Piano-vocal score; 178 p.; Also published Paris: S. Dufour, n.d.; Plate no. T.M.1647.; Contains annotations in pencil and page markers; cover carries the initials "E.G.," embossed in gold; title page autograph: "Marie Ris."; Language note: French (Box-folder S/8)
      - Zerline. Paris: G. Brandus, n.d., Piano-vocal score; 274 p.; Plate no. 8836.; Contains annotations in pencil.; Language note: French (Box-folder S/9)
    - Aubert, Louis
      - Suite brève, op. 6. Paris: A. Durand, 1912., Two pianos; score; 23 p.; Plate no. D. & F. 8484. (Box-folder 2/4)
    - Audran, Edmond
      - La mascotte. [=Krasnoe solnyshko.] Moscow: A. Gutkheĭl', n.d., Reduction for solo piano; score; 95 p.; Plate no. A.4394 G.; Contains also: Glinka, Mikhaĭl. Ruslan i Liudmila. Reduction for solo piano; score. Moscow: A. Gutkheĭl', n.d., 171 p. Plate no. K.2158 G. (Box-folder S/10)
    - Austin, Ernest
      - Stella-Mary dances, op. 58. London: J.H. Larway, 1919., Solo piano; score; 8 p.; Plate no. L.2326, .2327. (Box-folder 2/5)
    - Bach, Johann Sebastian
      - Beliebte Klavierstücke. Leipzig: C.F. Peters, n.d., Solo piano; score; 35 p.; Plate no. 7335. (Box-folder 3/1)
      - Clavierwerke, v. 1, 2 (Suites), v. 3 (Partitas). Leipzig: Steingraber, n.d., Solo piano; scores; [v. 1:] 123 p.; [v. 2:] 147 p.; [v. 3:] 113 p.; Three separately published volumes bound together.; Plate no. 149, 150, 151 (Box-folder S/40)
      - Clavierwerke, v. 4, 7 (Vermische Werke). Leipzig: Steingraber, n.d., Solo piano; scores; [v. 4:] 108 p.; [v. 7:] 159 p.; Two separately published volumes bound together.; Plate no. 152, 327 (Box-folder S/41)
      - Clavierwerke, v. 5, 6 (Das Wohltemperirte Clavier). Leipzig: Steingraber, n.d., Solo piano; scores; [v. 5:] 115 p.; [v. 6:] 133 p.; Two separately published volumes bound together.; Plate no. 153, 232 (Box-folder S/42)
      - Klavierwerke: Capriccio; Fantasie; etc. Leipzig: C.F. Peters, n.d., Solo piano; score; 35 p.; Plate no. 8857. (Box-folder 3/2)
      - Klavierwerke: Englische Suiten, nos. 1-3. Leipzig: C.F. Peters, n.d., Solo piano; score; 55 p.; Plate no. 8036. (Box-folder 3/3)
      - Klavierwerke: Englische Suiten, nos. 4-6. Leipzig: C.F. Peters, n.d., Solo piano; score; 61 p.; Plate no. 8037. (Box-folder 3/4)
      - Klavierwerke: Französische Suiten. Leipzig: C.F. Peters, n.d., Solo piano; score; 55 p.; Plate no. 8462. (Box-folder 3/5)
      - Klavierwerke: Partitas, nos. 1-3. Leipzig: C.F. Peters, n.d., Solo piano; score; 56 p.; Plate no. 8038. (Box-folder 3/6)
      - Klavierwerke: Partitas, nos. 4-6. Leipzig: C.F. Peters, n.d., Solo piano; score; 63 p.; Plate no. 8039. (Box-folder 3/7)
      - Klavierwerke: Supplement. Leipzig: C.F. Peters, n.d., Solo piano; score; 92 p.; Plate no. 6383. (Box-folder 3/8)
      - Geistliche Lieder und Arien. Leipzig: Breitkopf & Härtel, n.d., Arranged by E. Naumann for voice and piano; score; 81 p.; Plate no. J.S.B.VI.; Language note: German (Box-folder S/11)
      - Orchester-Suiten nos. 1-4. Leipzig: C.F. Peters, n.d., Arranged by M. Reger for two pianos; 96 p.; Plate no. 9140.; incomplete: part for piano I only (Box-folder 3/9)
      - Der Streit zwischen Phöbus und Pan. Leipzig: C.F. Peters, n.d., Piano-vocal score; 52 p.; Plate no. 8384.; Language note: German (Box-folder 3/10)
      - Das Wohltemperiertes Klavier, v. 1. Leipzig: C.F. Peters, n.d., Solo piano; score; 119 p.; Plate no. 7916. (Box-folder 4/1)
      - Das Wohltemperiertes Klavier, v. 2. Leipzig: C.F. Peters, n.d., Solo piano; score; 131 p.; Plate no. 7917. (Box-folder 4/2)
    - Balilla Pratella, Francesco
      - Musica futurista, op. 30. Bologna: F. Bongiovanni, 1912., Arranged for solo piano; score; 80 p.; Contains holograph inscription to Diaghilev from the composer on inside front cover page. (Box-folder 4/3)
    - Bantock, Granville
      - Old English suite. London: Novello, 1909., Solo piano; score; 25 p.; Plate no. 13114. (Box-folder 4/4)
      - The Pierrot of the minute. Leipzig: Breitkopf & Härtel, 1913., Arranged for solo piano; score; 21 p.; Plate no. V.A.3871. (Box-folder 4/5)
    - Bartók, Béla
      - Der holzgeschnitzte Prinz. Vienna: Universal, 1921., Reduction for solo piano; score; 70 p.; Plate no. U.E.6635. (Box-folder 4/6)
    - Bax, Arnold
      - In a vodka shop. London: Augener, 1915., Solo piano; score; 7 p.; Plate no. 14921. (Box-folder 4/7)
    - Beethoven, Ludwig van
      - Sonates choisies. Paris: Heugel, n.d., Solo piano; score; 162 p.; Plate no. C.O.113. (Box-folder 4/8)
      - Sonate, op. 27, no. 2. Paris: A. Durand, 1915., Solo piano; score; 15 p.; Plate no. D. & F.11115.; Also published in 1952 (Box-folder 4/9)
      - Symphonie pastorale. [Symphony, no. 6, op. 68, C minor.] Paris: A. Durand, n.d., Arranged for piano, four hands; score; 235 p.; Plate no. D. & F.9344.; Contains sparse annotations in pencil. (Box-folder S/12)
    - Berger, Rodolphe
      - Lettre valsée See: I.B. Collections, Box 2 (S/63), p. 67-68
      - Vdali ot Rodiny See: I.B. Collections, Box 2 (S/63), p. 67-68
      - Vinovaty rozy See: I.B. Collections, Box 3 (S/64), p. 68-69
      - Vliublennaia See: I.B. Collections, Box 2 (S/63), p. 67-68
    - Berlioz, Hector
      - Épisode de la vie d'un artiste, Grande symphonie fantastique. [Symphonie fantas-tique, op. 14.] ["Seconde édition revue et corrigée par F. Liszt."] Leipzig: F.E.C. Leuckart, n.d., Arranged for solo piano; score; 69 p.; Plate no. F.E.C.L.2893.; Contains annotations in pencil and in ink. (Box-folder 4/10)
      - Lelio, oder die Rückkehr ins Leben, op. 14b. Leipzig: Breitkopf & Härtel, 1903., Piano-vocal score; 16 p.; Plate no. V.A.1970.; Language note: French; Language note: German; Language note: English (Box-folder 4/11)
    - Bernard, M.
      - Piesni russkago naroda. Moscow: P. IUrgenson, 1886., Arranged for voice and piano; score; 157 p.; Plate no. 9285 T.426.; Language note: Russian (Box-folder 5/1)
    - Berners, Lord